Welcome back to the wonderful world of JupyterLab.
놀라운 유피터랩의 세계에 잘 오셨어요
And here we are in week two.
이제 2주 차예요
Day three.
3일째예요
Uh, bring up this notebook.
이 공책을 꺼내요
So we're talking conversational AI, also known as chat bot, and we're going to get right into it.
대화형 인공지능인 채팅 봇에 대해 알아보도록 하죠.
We start by doing our usual imports and we do our usual setting of our environment variables.
먼저 일반적인 가져오기와 환경 변수의 일반적인 설정으로 시작하죠
And we initialize OpenAI.
오픈AI를 초기화하죠
This time we will use OpenAI.
이번에는 오픈아이를 쓸 거예요
And you can have it as an exercise to switch in other models if you'd like to do so.
원한다면 다른 모델로 바꾸는 연습으로 사용할 수 있어요
So uh, going to start with the basic system message.
기본적인 시스템 메시지부터 시작할게요
You are a helpful assistant.
정말 도움이 되는 조수네요
All right.
좋아요
Now I want to talk for a bit about, um, message structure.
이제 비트 코드의 메시지 구조를 얘기해 볼게요
So first of all, uh, reminder of the structure of a prompt message to OpenAI.
먼저 오픈AI에 즉각 메시지를 보내는 구조를 다시 알려주세요
Uh, we've seen this many times now, and so you're probably thoroughly bored of me explaining it.
이런 건 이제 질리게 봤으니까 제가 설명하는 게 지겹겠죠
There it is.
저기 있네요
One more time.
한 번 더요
You know it well.
잘 아시네요
A list of dictionaries that give the system the user, and it can have an assistant responding and then
시스템에 사용자를 제공하는 사전 목록이죠 보조가 응답하고 그 다음 사용자가
the user and so on.
응답하는 거죠
And you may remember I mentioned there is something else to come, but for now.
다른 게 있다고 말씀드렸죠? 지금은 아니에요
System user assistant.
시스템 사용자 보조요
User assistant.
사용자 보조요
User assistant user and so on.
사용자 보조 사용자 등등이요
Uh, now we are going to write a function called chat.
이제 채팅이라는 함수를 쓸 거예요
And that function chat is going to take two inputs message and history.
그 함수 채팅은 두 개의 입력 메시지와 역사를 취할 거예요
Message represents the current, uh, message that is being being asked that chat needs to respond to.
이 메시지는 현재 채팅방이 답변해야 할 메시지를 나타내죠
And history has the history of all prior messages, all prior exchanges.
모든 이전의 메시지와 교류는 역사가 기록하고 있죠
And the structure of history is going to look like this.
역사의 구조는 이렇게 생겼을 거예요
It's going to be a list, a list that consists of lists.
목록이 될 겁니다 목록으로 구성된 목록이죠
And these sub lists like this are simply what the user said and what the assistant replied, what the
이런 하위 목록은 사용자가 뭐라고 대답하고 비서가 뭐라고 대답하고 사용자가 뭐라고
user said and what the assistant replied and so on.
대답하고 비서가 뭐라고 대답하는지 등이죠
So why am I asking you to do that?
왜 이런 부탁을 하는 걸까요?
Why are we going to write a function that looks like that with parameters, that arguments that look
왜 매개 변수가 있는 저런 함수를 써야 하죠? 왜 이런 인수가 있는 거죠?
like this?
그 대답은 그러디오가 채팅 유저 인터페이스와 함께 사용하기 위해 기대하는 특정한 유형의 함수이기
user interfaces.
때문이죠
And that's why Gradio expects us to write a function called chat that's going to take a message.
그래서 그라디오는 우리가 메시지를 받는 채팅이라는 함수를 쓰길 기대하죠
It's going to take history in this structure, and it will return the next the response, the response
이 구조에서 히스토리를 선택하고 응답을 반환할 겁니다 이 채팅에 대한
to this chat.
응답이요
So that's why we're thinking about that format.
그래서 그 형식을 고려하는 거죠
So our job for this function is going to be convert this kind of style of message into this.
이 함수에 대한 우리 작업은 이런 종류의 메시지를 여기로 변환하는 거죠
So we're going to need to iterate row by row through this structure and build this structure that you
이 구조를 통해 한 열씩 반복해야 합니다 위에 보이는 이 구조를 구축하고요
Hopefully that makes sense.
이해가 되면 좋겠네요
If not, it will make sense when I show you what that looks like.
그렇지 않다면 제가 보여드릴 때 이해가 될 거예요
So I'm defining a function called chat.
채팅이라는 함수를 정의하고 있어요
It takes a message that we got to respond to an input message, and it takes history of prior messages.
입력 메시지에 응답해야 하는 메시지가 필요합니다 이전 메시지의 기록도 필요하고요
So we first of all, we we set up our list of messages, which is going to be this guy.
먼저 메시지 목록을 설정합니다 이 사람이 되겠죠
And we populate it with the system prompt at the very start.
시작 부분에 시스템 프롬프트로 채우죠
Of course, then we are going to iterate through history.
물론 그런 다음 역사를 반복하겠죠
Each element of history again is one of these lists with two values.
역사의 각 요소는 두 개의 값을 가진 리스트 중 하나죠
So we're going to unpack that into user message assistant message.
사용자 메시지 비서 메시지에 그걸 풀어놓을게요
And then we append the user's message and the assistant message.
사용자 메시지와 보조 메시지를 추가해요
Uh each each time.
매번요
So each row from from history turns into two rows in this list.
역사에서 각 행은 이 목록에서 두 행으로 바뀌죠
One for the user, one for the assistant.
하나는 사용자를 위한 것 하나는 보조를 위한 것이죠
Hopefully that makes complete sense.
이해가 되면 좋겠네요
Now.
지금요
If not, you can always.
아니면 언제든 괜찮아요
Oh well, you don't need to.
그럴 필요 없어요
I was going to say you can always put in some print statements.
언제든 print문을 넣을 수 있다고 말하려 했어요
Uh, I had the foresight to put in some print statements myself.
제가 선견지명이 있어서 인쇄물도 몇 개 넣었어요 TED TED TED TED
So we will see this.
곧 보게 될 거예요
We're going to print the history And then we're going to print the messages.
히스토리를 프린트하고 메시지를 프린트할 거예요
So we get to see that too.
Get in get 역시 볼 수 있죠
Um, and then the next line is very familiar to you for this particular chat, uh, method at this point,
다음 줄은 이 채팅방에서 아주 익숙하실 텐데요 이 시점에서 이 메서드, 이
this function, sorry, at this point we are then going to take, um, this set of messages and we're
함수 죄송합니다, 이 시점에서 이 메시지 세트를 가지고 OpenAI를
going to call OpenAI with them.
호출할 거예요
So we do OpenAI chat dot completions, dot create.
OpenAI 채팅 .완성 .Create를 입력해요
We pass in the model, we pass in the messages, and we're going to say please stream results.
모델에서 전달하고 메시지를 전달하고 결과를 스트리밍해달라고 요청하죠
We might as well.
그렇게 하죠
And then we go through and we yield response.
그런 다음 검토하고 응답을 유도하죠
Um, so again this isn't actually a function.
다시 말씀드리지만 이건 함수가 아니에요
It's really a generator because we're going to be yielding the responses piece by piece.
하나씩 반응을 산출하기 때문에 발전기라고 할 수 있죠
Okay.
네
So what I want to do now is turn this into the kind of user interface that you saw in the slide a moment
이제 이걸 좀 전에 슬라이드에서 본 사용자 인터페이스로 바꿀 거예요 인스턴트 메시지 스타일
ago, a user interface which has an instant message style interaction.
상호 작용이 있는 사용자 인터페이스요
So obviously there's a bit of work to do there because we're going to have to, to to craft that kind
할 일이 많아요 비트가 계속 오는 메시지를
of, um, canvas with the messages that come one after another and figure out how to do that.
캔버스로 만들어서 어떻게 만들지 알아내야 하니까요
Um, based on the response that's coming back from this chat message.
이 채팅창에 올라온 반응을 보면요
Uh, I don't know if you've cottoned on, but I am, of course, fibbing.
눈치챘는지 모르겠지만 당연히 거짓말이죠
It's going to be really easy.
아주 쉬울 거예요
It's going to be a single line.
한 줄로 할 거예요
Uh, so Gradio comes with something called chat interface out of the box, and chat interface, uh,
그러디오는 채팅 인터페이스라는 독창적인 걸 내놓는데 채팅 인터페이스는
expects a single function which needs to have this structure.
이런 구조를 가진 단일 함수를 기대하죠
If you've written a function which takes a message and history in this particular format, then for
이 특정한 형식으로 메시지와 역사를 취하는 함수를 작성했다면 Gadio에선
Gradio it's just a single line of code.
코드 한 줄로 끝나죠
Uh, let's see if it's really that easy.
그렇게 쉬운지 볼까요?
I do need to remember to execute that so that we have defined our chat generator.
저걸 실행하는 걸 기억해야 합니다 채팅 생성기를 정의하도록요
And then we will launch our interface.
이제 인터페이스를 실행할 거예요
And here it is.
여기 있네요
Here is our chat interface.
채팅 인터페이스예요
Let's bring it up in a separate window, because I just prefer it that way.
다른 창으로 보여드리죠 그게 더 좋거든요
And we'll say, uh.
이렇게 말해요
Hello there.
안녕하세요
How can I assist you today?
무엇을 도와드릴까요?
I want to buy a tie.
넥타이 하나 사려고요
Great kind of tie are you looking for?
어떤 넥타이를 찾으세요?
Do you have a specific color, pattern or material?
특정한 색상, 패턴이나 재료가 있나요?
Uh, so you get the idea.
Get it, get it, get it. 대충 아시겠죠?
But let me just say, um, a red one red tie is a classic choice.
하지만 빨간색 넥타이는 고전적인 선택이에요
Here are a few options to consider.
몇 가지 선택지를 드리죠
And there comes the answer.
답이 나왔네요
Now, obviously the reason I said a red one is I wanted to demonstrate what you already know, which
빨간색을 고른 이유는 여러분이 이미 아는 걸 보여드리고 싶었기 때문이에요
is that it has context of this conversation and it knows what came before.
이 대화의 맥락을 갖고 있고 전에 뭐가 있었는지도 알죠
And one more time, it's a bit of an illusion to feel as if this thing has memory from when we first
다시 한번 말씀드리지만 비트가 처음 대화했을 때의 메모리를 가진 것 같아요
And I said, I want to buy a tie.
넥타이를 사고 싶다고 했어요
All that's happening is that every time we interact, that chat method, function generator, I get
우리가 상호 작용할 때마다 채팅 메서드, 함수 생성기가 결국엔 제대로 작동해요 get
it right eventually.
it
That chat generator is being called.
채팅 생성기가 호출됐어요
And what's being what's being passed in is the whole history so far.
지금까지의 역사를 전부 담고 있어요
And it's building that set of messages and that's what's being sent to OpenAI.
메시지 집합을 구축하고 오픈AI에 전송하는 거죠
So for each of our calls, the whole history is being provided.
통화 내역이 전부 제공되고 있어요
And that's why it has the context of what came before.
그래서 이전의 맥락이 있는 거예요
It's not as if the LLM, it's not as if GPT four is remembering that that 30s ago we said that.
LLM도 아니고 GPT 4도 아닙니다 30년 전에 했던 말을 기억하는 것도 아니죠
It's just that with every call, we pass it all in.
출동할 때마다 전부 전달해요
I'm sure it's obvious to you at this point.
이쯤 되면 눈치채셨겠지만요
So I'm sorry I'm belaboring it, but I think it's important to, to really rub it in.
장황하게 말해서 미안하지만 염장 지르는 게 중요하다고 생각해요
Um, and yeah, so you remember I have some print statements happening below which are going to be quite
네, 기억하세요? 아래에 print문이 있는데 지금은
chunky now, but let's just look at the the last one there.
꽤 두툼하죠 마지막 걸 보죠
So the last one said history is and then this is what Gradio sent us.
마지막 건 역사고 이건 그래디오가 보낸 거예요
And you'll see it's like uh, what we said, what it said, what we said, what it said.
그럼 보일 거예요 우리가 말한 대로 우리가 말한 대로요
Uh, and then we converted that into the right format for GPT four zero.
그리고 GPT 40을 위해 올바른 포맷으로 변환했죠
Uh, GPT four mini.
GPT 4 미니요
Um, we converted it into a list of, like, role system content.
역할 시스템 콘텐츠 목록으로 변환했어요
You're a helpful assistant.
정말 도움이 되는 조수네요
And then user said, hello there.
사용자가 안녕하세요라고 하죠
And the assistant replied, hello, how can I assist you today?
그러자 조수가 어떻게 도와드리면 되냐고 물었어요
And so on.
계속해서요
So that is what we turned it into.
그래서 이렇게 바꿨죠
All right, just before we go on, I'm going to have a quick tangent, but it is an important tangent.
좋아요, 시작하기 전에 잠깐 옆길로 새죠 중요한 거예요
So this isn't just me prattling on.
나 혼자 떠드는 게 아니에요
This is something which I want to sow a seed with you.
당신과 함께 그 씨앗을 뿌리고 싶어요
Something that we will come back to later and is an important point, um, which maybe, maybe something
나중에 다시 얘기하겠지만 중요한 부분이에요 어쩌면 당신이 생각해둔
that's been on your mind.
것일 수도 있고요
Um, or if not, it should be.
그렇지 않다면 그래야겠죠
Um, so just to mention, you might be thinking, so this structure, this system user assistant user.
언급하자면 이렇게 생각하실 수 있어요 시스템 사용자 비서가 이 구조에 대해서요
Uh, so is this.
이것도 그래요
Does this somehow get passed into the LLM in some structured way?
어떤 구조적인 방법으로 LLM에 Get이 전달되나요?
Like are we somehow when we when we provide this data to the LLM, is it being given maybe as a as a
우리가 어떻게든 이 데이터를 LLM에 제공할 때 사전이나 사전 목록
like a dictionary, a list of dictionaries in some way?
같은 어떤 식으로 제공되나요?
Um, because you may say, I thought Llms just took tokens.
LM은 토큰만 받는 줄 알았거든요
They just take a list of tokens and they generate the most likely next token.
토큰의 리스트를 선택하고 가장 가능성이 높은 다음 토큰을 생성하죠
So how does this whole list of dictionaries and so on, uh, translate to the world of tokens?
그럼 이 사전 전체 목록은 어떻게 토큰의 세계로 변환하죠?
And that would be a great thought if you had that thought.
그런 생각을 한다면 정말 좋을 거예요
Uh, very good.
아주 좋아요
Uh, and there's a simple answer, uh, it is just tokens that gets passed to the actual underlying
답은 간단합니다. 토큰을 전달하는 것입니다. 실제 GPT 4개,
GPT four, uh, GPT four LLM.
GPT 4개 LLM으로요.
What happens is that OpenAI turns this into a series of tokens, and it has special tokens, special
오픈AI는 이것을 토큰의 시리즈로 바꾸어 놓습니다. 특별한 토큰을 가지고 있는데 시스템 프롬프트의
ways of explaining that this is the beginning of a system prompt.
시작이라고 설명하는 방법이죠.
This is the beginning of a user and an assistance response.
사용자와 보조 대응의 시작이죠
It has some markup to say that, and it tokenizes that whole markup, including some special placeholder
그 말을 하는 마크업이 있고 그 전체 마크업을 토큰화합니다 LLM에 정보를 전달하는
tokens that sort of communicate inform the LLM.
특별한 자리 표시자 토큰을 포함해서요
We're now switching to system prompt mode.
이제 시스템 프롬프트 모드로 바꿀게요
Here's some system prompt text.
시스템 프롬프트 텍스트가 있네요
And now we're out of system prompt mode.
이제 시스템 프롬프트 모드에서 벗어났어요
Now we're doing a user message and so on.
사용자 메시지 같은 걸 하고 있죠
So this structure is what we send the OpenAI API.
이 구조가 OpenAI API 전송이에요
It converts it into tokens.
패로 변환하죠
And it's those tokens that then get fed to the LLM to predict the next token.
이 토큰들이 LLM에 입력되어 get 다음 토큰을 예측하죠
And you might say, okay, I hear you, I get that.
Get it, get it, get it's right, get's right, right.
But how does the LLM know that this particular special token means system message and should interpret
그런데 LLM은 이 특별한 토큰이 시스템 메시지를 의미한다는 것과 이를 높은 수준의 지시로 해석해야
that to be its its high level directive?
한다는 것을 어떻게 알까요?
And how does it know that this token means user and this means assistant and so on.
이 토큰이 사용자를 의미하고 이건 비서를 의미한다는 걸 어떻게 알까요?
Like like what gives it that ability is that, like, baked into its architecture in some way?
어떤 식으로든 그런 능력을 아키텍처에 구현한 건가요?
Uh, and there's a very simple answer to that, which is that.
그에 대한 답은 아주 간단해요
No, it's just because that's how it's been trained.
아뇨, 그렇게 훈련받았으니까요
It's been trained with lots of data, with that structure, with millions of examples like that.
많은 데이터와 구조로 훈련되었고 수백만 개의 예로 훈련되었어요
And it's learned through training that when it's being given a specific directive in a system instruction,
시스템 지침에서 특정 지침을 받았을 때 다음 토큰과 반응은
the most likely next token, the most likely response is going to be one that adheres to that system
시스템 프롬프트를 준수하는 것이라는 것을 배우게 되죠
There's I've oversimplified.
너무 단순화했어요
There's some, uh, more nuance there to do with with things like the technique that is like chef and
뉘앙스가 좀 더 있어요 셰프 같은 기술과 관련해서요
For for those that know all this stuff are listening and saying, oh, it's a bit oversimplified, but
비트 박스를 아는 사람들은 너무 단순화됐다고 하겠지만 그게 일반적인
it's the general idea.
개념이에요
It's the basic idea.
기본 아이디어예요
This structure is this sort of the API structure.
이 구조는 일종의 API 구조예요
This is how we communicate to OpenAI that that's what we want to do.
오픈AI에 우리가 원하는 걸 이렇게 전달하는 거죠
And OpenAI takes that structure and turns it into tokens.
오픈아이는 그 구조를 토큰으로 바꾸죠
So to to sort of take a step to, to the very beginning, Gradio gives us data in this format.
그럼 이제 처음으로 넘어가서 그라디오는 이런 포맷의 데이터를 주죠
We map that to this format, which is what we send OpenAI and OpenAI converts that to tokens, including
이것을 OpenAI에 보내는 이 형식에 매핑합니다 OpenAI는 이것을 특별한 토큰을 포함한 토큰으로
some special tokens.
변환하죠
It's that that goes into the LLM for the whole conversation so far, for everything, every time it
지금까지의 모든 대화에 해당하는 LLM으로 들어갑니다 대화 전체를
gets the entire conversation, and then it generates the most plausible next sequence of tokens that
담을 때마다 가장 그럴듯한 다음 토큰 배열을 생성하죠 그다음으로 나올 가능성이
are most likely to come after that.
가장 큰 토큰요
Um, and that is what gets returned to us that we then assume represents the assistance response.
그게 우리에게 돌아오는 거고 우린 그걸 원조 대응이라고 생각하죠
So I realized that was quite a long sidebar.
그래서 그게 꽤 긴 사이드바라는 걸 깨달았죠
It's very important, foundational understanding.
아주 중요한 기본적 이해예요
And we will come back to that when we, particularly when we look at open source models.
다시 돌아오죠 특히 오픈 소스 모델을 볼 때요
And we're actually going to see these kinds of generated tokens, these special tokens ourselves.
생성된 토큰들을 직접 볼 것입니다. 특별한 토큰들을요.
So with that, I'm going to pause it until the next video when we're going to press ahead building this
다음 비디오까지 잠시 멈추겠습니다 그때 이 챗봇을 만들
chatbot out.
거예요